<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triall and examination of the Lord Major of London on Munday last, being the second of this instant Aprill, 1649. at the Bar of the House of Commons with His Lordships speech, concerning the Kingly office; and the censure, resolution, and votes of the Parliament, touching his contempt, their fining of him 2000.li. His body to be committed prisoner to the Tower of London, and to be degraded of Mayoralty. Also, the Princes message and proposals to the Parliament of Scotland, in answer to the letter sent by their commissioners; and the resolution of the estates at Edenburgh, concerning his Highnesse, to be sent to the Parliament of England. Likewise the proclaiming of a new Act, the rising of 5000 gourdons in the North, and their surrounding of Lieut. Gen. Lesley, and the Parliaments forces, and declaring for Charles the second.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94833</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E549_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205617</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864945</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864945</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117178</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94833)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117178)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 85:E549[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triall and examination of the Lord Major of London on Munday last, being the second of this instant Aprill, 1649. at the Bar of the House of Commons with His Lordships speech, concerning the Kingly office; and the censure, resolution, and votes of the Parliament, touching his contempt, their fining of him 2000.li. His body to be committed prisoner to the Tower of London, and to be degraded of Mayoralty. Also, the Princes message and proposals to the Parliament of Scotland, in answer to the letter sent by their commissioners; and the resolution of the estates at Edenburgh, concerning his Highnesse, to be sent to the Parliament of England. Likewise the proclaiming of a new Act, the rising of 5000 gourdons in the North, and their surrounding of Lieut. Gen. Lesley, and the Parliaments forces, and declaring for Charles the second.</title>
                  <author>Reynardson, Abraham, Sir, 1590-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Williamson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reynardson, Abraham, --  Sir, 1590-1661.</term>
               <term>England and Wales --  Parliament --  House of Commons.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117178:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Triall and Examination Of the Lord Major of LONDON <hi>ON Munday</hi> laſt, being the ſecond of this inſtant <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1649. at the Bar of the Houſe of COMMONS <hi>WITH</hi> His Lordſhips Speech, concerning the <hi>Kingly Office; AND</hi> The Cenſure, Reſolution, and Votes of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his contempt, their fining of him 2000. <hi>li.</hi> His Body to be committed priſoner to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and to be degraded of Mayoralty.</p>
            <p>ALSO, The Princes Meſſage and Propoſals to the Parliament of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in anſwer to the Letter ſent by their <hi>Commiſſioners;</hi> and the Reſolution of the Eſtates at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Highneſſe, to be ſent to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe the proclaiming of a new Act, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> riſing of 5000 Gourdons in the North, and their ſurrounding of Lieut. Gen. <hi>Leſley,</hi> and the Parliaments forces, and declaring for CHARLES the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Williamſon,</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="trial">
            <pb facs="tcp:117178:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117178:2"/>
            <head>The Tryall and Examination of the Lord Major of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> at the Bar of the Houſe of Commons, on Munday laſt, with his Speech concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Kingly Government.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord Major of the City of <hi>London,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſummoned by the Parl. of <hi>England</hi> to attend that honorable Houſe, for his contempt, in diſobeying the Orders of Parliament, and neglecting and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſing to proclaim the Act for aboliſhing the kingly office in England and Ireland, within the ſaid City; in order whereunto, his Lordſhip was brought to the Barre of the Houſe of Commons; and after ſome Queries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, concerning his non-performance thereof, He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, <hi>That according to the Oath of Allegeance which he had taken, he could not (in Conſcience) proclaim the ſaid Act for the aboliſhing of the Kingly Office, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Kingſhip,</hi> declaring. <hi>That the buſineſſe was onely proper for the Sheriff of the City.</hi> And being remanded from the Bar, the Houſe voted as followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved by the Commons of</hi> England <hi>aſſembled in Parl.</hi> That the Lord Major of the City of <hi>London,</hi> for his contempt in diſobeying the Orders of Parl. bee fined
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117178:3"/>2000. l. <hi>Reſolved, &amp;c.</hi> That he be committed priſoner to the Tower of <hi>London</hi> for two months, and be degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of Mayralty. <hi>Reſolved, &amp;c.</hi> That an Order be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with drawn up, and immediatly ſent to the Common-councell of the ſaid city, requiring and impowring them to elect a new Major with all ſpeed; and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto, the ſeverall companies within the ſaid city are required to meet (this day) for the election thereof.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="declaration">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>A new Declaration from the parl. of</hi> Scotland.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sir,</hi> The Committee of Eſtates conveened at Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, begin to wave and deviate from their former Reſolutions for the inveſting of <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, &amp; are now reſolved to aſſume the power of a free Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, their propoſals to their young <hi>King</hi> taking no effect; for upon the repreſenting of the ſame by their commiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſioners. His Highneſſe was pleaſed to return this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> That he was not (as yet) ſatisfied in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence touching the lawfulneſſe of the covenant, &amp; their Uniformity of presbytery, and therfore could not give them a poſitive anſwer, touching his preſent ſigning &amp; entring into covenant, deſiring further reſpite of time to conſult thereon. 2 That he gives the parl. of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land many thanks for their Offers and Loyalty to aſſiſt and protect him, and for their fidelity and cordial affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions towards the preſervation of Soveraignty, in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging him their true and lawfull King by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtfull Succeſſion; but withall deſires, that they will take the advice of him and his Councel, in reference to Religion, Crown and kingdoms; to the end, that both he and they, may (with ſtability of mind) ſix their Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions upon a Rock of unmoveable principles. The Eſtates conveened having received this meſſage, voted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117178:3"/>it unſatisfactory, and that 10000 Horſe and Foot ſhould be forthwith put into a poſture, for a conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with England, offenſive or defenſive againſt all oppoſition to either Nations, from abroad or at home and have nominated and made choiſe of commiſſioners to be expedited to the parliament of England with a meſſage, for the faciliating of this work, and intimating unto them the tranſaction of affairs in this Nation. For ſo ſoon as they underſtood their young Kings reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he was determined for Ireland, they begin u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally to decline their firſt engagement, and have cauſed an Edict or Act to be proclaimed at the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Croſſe, exhibiting all perſons whatſoever from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, abetting, or contriving any thing tending to the inthroning of <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> the ſecond, untill ſuch time that he ſhall give full ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in matters of Religion, and other publike affairs, tending to the ſafty and preſervation of this <hi>Kirk</hi> and <hi>Kingdom;</hi> inſomuch, that the Royal parsy are much diſcontented thereat, &amp; upon the proclaiming thereof, aſſembled together, fell upon the Bayliffs, and other magiſtrates of the city, killed and wounded many, crying out, <hi>God bleſſe King</hi> Charles <hi>the ſecond.</hi> But by the ſpeedy coming in of the trayned Bands, the adverſe party were routed, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them apprehended, and committed to ſafe cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. But from the North we have received a ſtrong al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum, which is, that 5000 Gourdons have Bodied, &amp; have ſurrounded Lieu. Gen. <hi>Leſley,</hi> and that 2000 more are come in to their aſſiſtance, commanded by the L. <hi>Oglesby,</hi> declare for <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond. The Lieu. Gen. is in very great ſtraights, but the Committee of Eſtates are ſending 6000 Horſe and Foot to relieve him; you will hear of ſudden action.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Edenburgh</hi> 
                        <date>28. <hi>Martii,</hi> 1649.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:117178:4"/>
            <p>Sir, The Prince is very numerous in ſhipping, the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> with 20 Sayle of ſhips, lies floting up and downe the Weſt Ridings; inſomuch that no ſhips can paſſe nor eſcape his fury; For, few days ſince, a Fleet of Marchants ſayling towards the Lands-End, were ſet upon by the Lord <hi>Hoptons</hi> Squadron, who coming within ſhot of them gave them a broad ſide; but were anſwered with the like volley from them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; inſomuch, that they came to a hot diſpute, the fight continuing many hours, and after the exchange of ſeverall tokens from the Sons of <hi>Mars,</hi> the L. <hi>Hopton</hi> held off, refuſing to fight any longer, and ſteered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Iſle of <hi>Scilley;</hi> the famous ſhip called the <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pepper,</hi> &amp; about 6 more, chaſed them about 2 leagues, ſunk three of them, the reſt eſcaped: in this fight many were ſlain and wounded on both ſides, and one of the Marchants ſhips ſunk alſo, above 100 Mariners ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their lives in this engagement. The fight beings en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Marchants Fleet hoyſted ſayl, &amp; ſteerd toward the Lands-End; which being done, the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> put to Sea again, and (being thirſty of revenge) after few hours ſayl, he eſpyed a prey, who with fury and rage made towards them, gave them a broad ſide, ſurroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them (although 8 in number) inſomuch that three of them were cloſe beſet, and ſeverall times ready to board; but by their undanted courage and gallantry repulſed them, diſputed the Onſet, and were in a good way to have got ſafe from them, but a ſupply of more ſhipping coming afterwards from <hi>Scilley,</hi> joyned with the firſt Squadron, who by their great potency and ſtrength overpowred them, boarded the ſhips, ſeized on all the goods and marchandize, tying every man back to back, ſhutting them under Decks, and carryed them priſoners to the Iſle of Scilley, where they now
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117178:4"/>remain under the barbarous reſtraint of Sir <hi>George Carteret,</hi> the Governour; <hi>God in his due time reſtore them to liberty, and grant them patience, in this their time of affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ſpeedy and timely ſupplies of ſhipping be not haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned forth, it is to be feared, they will become ſole ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Brittiſh Seas. Since their taking of the late prize, they have met with another <hi>Bristoll</hi> ſhip, richly laden with cloth, which the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> hath diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted amongſt the ſea men and ſouldiers. He is now ſayled towards <hi>Milford</hi> Haven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but by the way, hee ſtruck in at a Creek neer <hi>Pendennis,</hi> where he landed many of his men for the fetching in of proviſion, and other accommodation; but before they could facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and accompliſh their Deſign, the <hi>Parliaments</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at <hi>Pendennis</hi> having notice thereof, a conſiderable party of Horſe and Foot were forthwith commanded out, who haſtned to welcome their coming in, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to get between them and the water, for the intercepting of their paſſage, but through the maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Corniſh men their deſign was almoſt fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated; for after few hours march they were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and the Enemy in a poſture to receive them, who upon their neer approach ſaluted each other with the tokens of <hi>Mars,</hi> and after a hot conflict the <hi>Hoptoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> retreated within command of their Ships, our men purſued, kiled 19. wounded many, and made good their retreat with the loſſe of 7 men. Their Ordnance did much retard our purſuit, by which meanes moſt of them got ſafe aboard having many Boats in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to receive them; otherwiſe few of them had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed: ſome of the Land ſouldiers deſerted them at their coming aſhore, who ſay, That the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> is commander in chief of that Squadron, and of all the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117178:5"/>Land forces thereunto belonging, and that his Colours, (or Enſigns) are yelow, with black bulets in the midſt, and on the top thereof, this Motto written in Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of Gold, <hi>For Charles the ſecond.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Bristol</hi> 
                  <date>29 <hi>Martii,</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>A new Declaration concerning Lieu. col. <hi>Lilburn.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The Commons of <hi>England</hi> aſſembled in parliament doth declare, That the Authors, Contrivers, and Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of the late paper, entituled, <hi>The ſecond part of</hi> Englands <hi>new Chains,</hi> &amp;c. are guilty of high treaſon, &amp; ſhall be proceeded againſt as traytors; and that all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever that ſhall joyn with, or adhere there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and hereafter voluntarily ayd or aſſiſt the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, Framers, and Contrivers of the aforeſaid paper, in the proſecution thereof, ſhall be eſteemed as tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to the Commonwealth, and be proceeded againſt accordingly.</p>
            <p>Lieut. col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> (ſince his confinement to the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer) hath had a conference with ſome members of the Army, and hath declared many propheticall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, in relation to their proceedings, ſaying, that they are in the wrong way, and that his forwardneſſe and zeal proceeded from no deſign, or particular inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, but reall intentions of publike good to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <closer>Imprimatur <signed>T. JENNINGS</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
